A Guide to the Papers of Rufus Ivory Cole 1900-1966
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Papers of Rufus Ivory Cole 1900-1966
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-19
1 1/3 linear feet, 3 Hollinger boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Staige Davis IV.
Biographical/Historical Information
Rufus Ivory Cole was born in Rowsburg, Ohio, on April 30, 1872. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1896 and attended the Johns Hopkins Medical School, graduating in 1899. At Hopkins he came under the influence of faculty members such as William Osler, William H. Welch, and Lewellys Barker. As a resident at Hopkins, Cole was in charge of a biological laboratory where he studied typhoid fever. He married Annie Hegeler in 1908, the same year he was appointed the Director of the Hospital of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, the first hospital in the U.S. devoted primarily to the investigation of disease. The Hospital itself opened in October 1910 with 50 beds. Cole remained at the Hospital until 1937. His medical research centered on problems relating to immunity to diseases of the respiratory system, particularly pneumonia. In retirement he wrote a two volume work titled Human History: The Seventeenth Century and the Stuart Family. Cole died on April 20, 1966.
Scope and Content
Cole's collection contains correspondence, including several postcards from his grandsons and one with "Mrs. Rufus Cole" printed on it; reprints of journal articles, mainly ones written by Cole; and biographical memoirs and honorary programs related to Sir William Osler, William H. Welch, William Stewart Halstead, Samuel James Meltzer, Harvey Cushing, William George MacCallum, Oswald Theodore Avery, Simon Flexner, Thomas Milton Rivers, Max Broedel, and Allen O. Whipple.
Arrangement
Varied.
Contents List
- Letter from William E. MacCallum to Rufus Ivory Cole June 6, 1916, 1 ALS (Box-folder 001-001)
- Letter from Frederick F. Russell to Rufus Ivory Cole January 20, 1930, 1 TDS (Box-folder 001-002)
- Letter from C.B. Farrar to Rufus Ivory Cole July 16, 1959, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-003)
  Re:the erection of Sir William Osler marker near his birthplace
- Letter from Eric A. Linnel to Rufus Ivory Cole August 7, 1959, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-004)
- Letter from Eric A. Linnel to Rufus Ivory Cole June 6, 1961, [n.d.], 1 TL,1 ALS, 1 photo (Box-folder 001-005)
  Re:the erection of Sir William Osler marker near his birthplace; photo of marker
- Letter from Cecile Desbarats [Librarian at the Osler Library, McGill University, Montreal, Canada]to Rufus Ivory Cole September 3, 1959, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-006)
- Postal card from Rufus [Botzow] to Grandpa [Rufus Ivory Cole] September 4, 1963, 1 AC (Box-folder 001-007)
  From Rufus [grandchild]to Grandpa [Rufus Ivory Cole]
- Postal card from Bill [Botzow] to Grandpa [Rufus Ivory Cole] September 4, 1963, 1 AC (Box-folder 001-008)
  From Bill [grandchild] to Grandpa [Rufus Ivory Cole]
- Postal card from Jose [s.n.] to Rufus Ivory Cole September 4, 1963, 1 AC (Box-folder 001-009)
  From Jose to Dr. Cole [Rufus Ivory Cole]
- Letter from Cecile Desbarats [Librarian at the Osler Library, McGill University, Montreal, Canada] to Rufus Ivory Cole October 7, 1963, 1 TLS(carbon copy) (Box-folder 001-010)
- Letter from Rufus Ivory Cole to Cecile Desbarats [Librarian at the Osler Library, McGill University, Montreal, Canada] November 4, 1963, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-011)
- Letter from Cecile Desbarats [Librarian at the Osler Library, McGill University, Montreal, Canada] to Rufus Ivory Cole December 24, 1963, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-012)
- Letter from Wilburt C. Davison to Rufus Ivory Cole November 14, 1949, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-013)
- The Papers of Rufus Cole 1904-1960 November 4, 1963, 1 TD (Box-folder 001-014)
  (carbon copy) stained and damaged 13 pages Initialed c.c.s.
- Selected Papers by Dr. Cole [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 001-015)
  ( copy) 2 pages
- Journal reprint from American Medicine, "Pneumococcus Arthritis" by Rufus I. Cole May 31, 1902, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-016)
- Journal reprint from Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, "Blood Cultures in Pneumonia" by Rufus I. Cole June 1902, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-017)
- Journal reprint from Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, "Note on the case of Bacillus aerogenes capsulatus, in which the organism was demonstrated in the circulating blood during life" by Rufus I. Cole October 1902, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-018)
- Journal reprint from Johns Hopkins Hospital Reports, "Typhoid meningitis" by Rufus I. Cole 1904, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-019)
- Journal reprint from Journal of Infectious Diseases, "Experimental Streptococcus Arthritis in relation to the etiology of acute articular rheumatism" by Rufus I. Cole November 5, 1904, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-020)
- Journal reprint from New York Medical Journal, "Aetiology of Acute Articular Rheumatism" by Rufus I. Cole March 17, 1906, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-021)
- Journal reprint from Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, "Note on the Production of an Agglutinating Serum for Blood Platelets" by Rufus I. Cole June-July 1907, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-022)
- Journal reprint from International Clinics, "Vaccine Treatment of Infectious Diseases" by Rufus I. Cole 1907, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-023)
- Journal reprint from Archives of Internal Medicine, "Pneumococcus Infection and Lumbar Pneumonia" by Rufus I. Cole July 1914, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-024)
- Journal reprint from New York Medical Journal, "Pneumococcus Infection and Immunity" by Rufus I. Cole January 2 and 9 1915, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-025)
- Journal reprint from New York State Medical Journal, "Present Status of Serum Therapy" by Rufus I. Cole August 1917, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-026)
- Journal reprint from Science, "The Modern Hospital and Medical Progress" by Rufus Cole August 6, 1926, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-027)
- Journal reprint from the Annals of Medical History, "Francesco Redi (1626-1697) Physician, Naturalist, Poet" by Rufus Cole; tear sheets from the Annals of Medical History, "Francesco Redi (1626-1697) Physician, Naturalist, Poet" by Rufus Cole 1926, 1 Journal reprint, 1 set of tear sheets (Box-folder 001-028)
- Journal reprint from Bulletin of Johns Hopkins Hospital, "Special Meeting of the Johns Hopkins Hospital Historical Club. Presentation to the hospital of Memorial Plaque of Sir William Osler-Teacher and Student" September, 1927, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-029)
- Journal reprint from Sir William Osler Memorial Volume, "Sir William Osler-Teacher and Student" by Rufus Cole, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-030)
- Lecture reprint from De Lamar Lectures 1927-28, "Acute Pulmonary Infections" by Rufus I. Cole 1928, 1 Lecture reprint (Box-folder 001-031)
- Journal reprint from Science, "Progress of Medicine during the Past Twenty-five Years as Exemplified by the Harvard Society Lectures" by Rufus Cole June 20, 1930, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-032)
- Journal reprint from Proceedings from the Institute of Medicine, "The Nature of Pneumonia" by Rufus Cole November 27, 1931, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-033)
- Journal reprint from Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, "The President's Address" by Rufus Cole 1931, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-034)
- Journal reprint from Annals of Internal Medicine, "The Treatment of Pneumonia" by Rufus Cole July 1936, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-035)
- Journal reprint from The Military Surgeon, "Possibilities for Pneumonia Control as Indicated by Present Scientific Knowledge" by Rufus Cole October 1937, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-036)
- Journal reprint from Science, "The Practice of Medicine" by Rufus Cole October 7, 1938, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-037)
- Journal reprint from the Journal of the Michigan State Medical Society, "Medical Societies and Medical Progress" by Rufus Cole January 1941, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-038)
- Journal reprint from the Bulletin of the Johns Hopkins Hospital, "Perfectionism in Medicine" by Rufus Cole August 1946, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 001-039)
- Journal reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, by Rufus Ivory Cole and J.C. Meakins, "The Treatment of Gonorrhoeal Arthritis by Vaccines" June-July 1907, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-001)
- Journal reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, by Rufus Ivory Cole and M.R.Smirnov, "The Pro-infective ('Aggressive') Action of Normal Blood-serum" September 1908, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-002)
- Journal reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin, by Rufus Ivory Cole and Arthur Bond Cecil, "The Axillary Diastolic Murmur in Aortic Insufficiency" December 1908, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-003)
- Journal reprint from the Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, by Rufus Ivory Cole and A.R. Dochez, "Report of Studies on Pneumonia" 1913, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-004)
- Journal reprint from the Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, by Rufus Ivory Cole and W.G. MacCallum, "Pneumonia at a Base Hospital" 1918, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-005)
- Program in honor of William H. Welch Belvedere Hotel, Baltimore, Md. April 2, 1910, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 002-006)
- Journal reprint from the Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, "Program of the Presentation of the Kober Medal of the Association of American Physicians to William H. Welch" May 4, 1927, 1 Journal reprint (Box-folder 002-007)
- Milbank Memorial Fund for the Committee on the Celebration of the Eightieth Birthday of Doctor William Henry Welch, "The Eightieth Birthday of William Henry Welch" 1930-1931, 1 Program (Box-folder 002-008)
  Removed from folder: William H. Welch Lectures, delivered at the Mt. Sinai Hospital, New York City, October 17-18, 1930; "Sir William Osler: Reminiscences," by Wilburt C. Davison, July 1949; Biographical Memoir of William Henry Welch, 1850-1934, by Simon Flexner, 1943.
- Memorial Meeting in honor of William H. Welch, delivered at the University Club, Baltimore, May 22, 1934 1935, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 002-009)
- Dust Jacket, William H. Welch and the Heroic Age of American Medicine, by Simon Flexner and James Thomas Flexner 1954, 1 Dust Jacket (Box-folder 002-010)
- News clipping, New York Times Book Review, July 4, 1954, "The Growing Up of American Medicine," a review of books re: William H. Welch and others July 4, 1954, 1 News clipping (Box-folder 002-011)
- "Memoirs of the National Academy of Sciences: Samuel James Meltzer, 1851-1920" by William H. Howell 1927, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 002-012)
- Journal Supplement to the Bulletin of Johns Hopkins Hospital, "Dr. Halsted" by George W. Heuer February 1952, 1 Journal Supplement (Box-folder 002-013)
  William Stewart Halsted, September 23, 1852-September 7, 1922
- Menu, Dinner in honor of William Osler, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, New York City May 2, 1905, 1 Dinner Menu (Box-folder 003-001)
- Journal Reprint from Baltimore Evening Sun, "Sir William Osler" by Lewellys F. Barker December 1919, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-002)
- Journal Reprint from The Nation, "Osler" by William S. Thayer January 24, 1920, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-003)
- Journal Reprint from the Canadian Journal Of Medicine and Surgery, "Osler at Johns Hopkins" by Lewellys F. Barker March 1920, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-004)
- Journal from the Canadian Medical Association, "Sir William Osler Memorial Number" July 1920, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 003-005)
- Journal Reprint from the Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, "Influence of Dr. William Osler on American Medicine" by George Martin Kober 1920, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-006)
- Journal Reprint from the Transactions of the Association of American Physicians, "Dr. William Osler as a Book Reviewer; his attitude towards hospitals" [n.d.], 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-007)
- Journal Reprint from the Bulletin of Johns Hopkins Hospital, "Presentation of Hospital Memorial Plaque of Sir William Osler," at a special meeting of the Johns Hopkins Hospital Historical Club January 19, 1925, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-008)
- Pamphlet, International Association of Medical Museums, "Memorial Number in Memoriam: Personal Reminiscences of Sir William Osler" by S. Adolphus Knopf 1926, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 003-009)
  with inscription to R.I. Cole from A.S. Knopf
- Journal Reprint from the Boston Medical and Surgical Journal, "The Influence of Osler on the Practice of Medicine" by Joseph H. Pratt January 20, 1927, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-010)
- Journal Reprint from the Academy of Medicine Bulletin, Silver Jubilee Number, "William Osler" by Archibald Malloch May 1932, Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-011)
  Duplicate removed from folder.
- Journal Reprint from the Bulletin of the Medical Library Association, "The President's Address: at Osler's Shrine" by W.W. Francis October 1937, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-012)
- Program, Canadian Medical Association, "The Fifth Osler Memorial Oration" by Charles D. Darfitt 1942, 1 Program (Box-folder 003-013)
- Journal, Archives of Internal Medicine, Sir William Osler Memorial Number July 1949, 1 Journal (Box-folder 003-014)
- Journal Reprint from the Proceedings of the Institute of Medicine of Chicago, "William Osler, the Humanist," by John F. Fulton October 15, 1949, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-015)
- Journal Reprint from the Archives of Internal Medicine, "Excerpts from Osler, a Mosaic of Bedside Aphorisms and Writings" by William Bennett Bean 1949, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-016)
  inscribed to Dr. Cole from William B. Bean
- Journal Reprint from the Journal of the Association American of Medical Colleges, "Osler's Influence," by Wilburt C. Davison May 1950, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-017)
- Pamphlet from the National Academy of Sciences, "Biographical Memoir of Harvey Cushing, 1869-1939" by William George MacCallum 1941, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 003-018)
- Pamphlet from the National Academy of Sciences, "Biographical Memoir of William George MacCallum, 1874-1944" by W.T. Longcope 1945, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 003-019)
  Inscribed to Rufus I. Cole from W.T. Longcope
- Oswald T. Avery, Selections from the Bibliography of 1909-1932 [n.d.], TD (carbon copy) (Box-folder 003-020)
- Journal Reprint, Biographical Memoirs of Fellows, the Royal Society, "Oswald Theodore Avery 1877-1955" by R.J. Durbos November 1956, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-021)
- Journal Reprint from the Journal of General Microbiology, "Obituary Notice, Oswald Theodore Avery, 1877-1955" by Colin MacLeod December 1957, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-022)
- Journal Reprint from Perspectives in Biology and Medicine, "Oswald Theodore Avery and DNA" by Alvin F. Coburn Summer 1969, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-023)
  with inscription from Coburn to John S. Davis [grandson of Cole and collection donor]
- Journal Reprint, Occasional Papers by the Faculty and Friends of The Rockefeller Institute, "The Johns Hopkins University and The Rockefeller Institute Allies in the March of Science," address delivered at the Rockefeller Institute April 3, 1959 by George W. Corner 1959, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-024)
  on the occasion of a dinner meeting of the Association of the Johns Hopkins Alumni
- Journal Reprint from the Monographs of the Rockefeller Institute ,"Acute Lobar Pneumonia, Prevention of Serum Treatment" by Oswald T. Avery, H.T. Chickering, Rufus Cole and A.R. Dochez October 16, 1917, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-025)
- Journal Reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin ,"Amboceptors and Complement in Typhoid Sera" by Henry S. Denison September 1908, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-026)
- Journal Reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin ,"The Opsonins in Typhoid Immunity" by H. Klein, Leipzig June-July 1907, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-027)
- Journal Reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin ,"Tuberculo-opsonic Index and Treatment by Tuberculin" by P.C. Jeans and A.W. Sellands June-July 1907, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-028)
- Journal Reprint from the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin ,"The Method of 'Fixation of Complement' in the Diagnosis of Meningococcus and gonococcus Infection" by J.C. Meakins June-July 1907, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-029)
- 1.Journal Reprint from Archives of Pathology, "Obituary-- Simon Flexner, 1863-1946" by Eugene L. Opie; 2. Journal Reprint from the Royal Society, Obituary Notices of Fellows of, "Simon Flexner 1863-1946" by Peyton Rous The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, June 12, 1946 1946, 1949, 2 Journal Reprints (Box-folder 003-030)
  Removed from folder: "Memorial Meeting for Simon Flexner" with Speakers Herbert S. Gasser, Learned Hand, Peyton Rous, Raymond B. Fosdick and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., June 12, 1946
- Journal Reprint from National Academy of Science Biographical Memoirs, "Thomas Milton Rivers, 1888-1962" by Frank L. Horsfall, Jr. 1965, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-031)
- Journal Reprint from the Bulletin of the Medical Library Association, "Max Broedel, 1870-1941, Director of the First Department of Art as Applied to Medicine in the World" by Thomas S. Cullen 1945, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-032)
- Proceedings of the Allen O. Whipple Portrait Presentation Dinner, "In Honor of Allen O. Whipple, M.D." Hotel Plaza, New York City September 22, 1952, 1 Proceedings (Box-folder 003-033)
- Journal Reprint from Virginia Medical Monthly, "Steriod Hormones and Rheumatism" by John Staige Davis, Jr. and Harry Bartfield July 1952, 1 Journal Reprint (Box-folder 003-034)
- Postal Card with home address of Mrs. Rufus Cole August 24, 1960, 1 AC (Box-folder 003-035)
  [Annie Hegeler Cole] note: History of Johns Hopkins Hospital Vols I & II to Mr. Hegeler, August 24, 1960
- (Box-folder 003-036)